Civilizational State (Part One)
My basic idea is that a “civilizational state” inherits abundant historical and cultural legacies,
so it will not follow every step of other countries.
In some cases, people will lose their own features in internationalization.
On the road to reform, what can we change and what should we hold up to?
What positive experience did our present Socialist System with Chinese Characteristics absorb?
Institutional acceptance must no longer be a vague concept. It must be established.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Bullet comment is good design.
Look at this comment.
- The one in red?
- Yes.
"Every country is built upon a different history, environment, and people,
"so naturally, every country has its unique path of development.
"Even the democracies in the US and the UK are different from each other,
"and they take different paths as well,
"so why can't they tolerate a different Chinese path?"
Working in media, we always meet people working in Western media.
We have all been abroad.
In my opinion, they just think you are different from them.
You don't adopt western democracy in the form of its political and social systems.
So, you are wrong in everything.
Everything is bad.
In 2004, a producer and a host of ITV flew to Beijing on October 1st.
I invited her: "Let's go to visit the Forbidden City."
You all know the Forbidden City on October 1st each year. [the National Day holiday]
The two subway stations "Tiananmen East" and "Tiananmen West" are closed.
You have to get off at the Xidan station.
Then, you follow the crowd.
The huge crowd will push you to go forward.
So, all along the way, she kept saying: "Oh, my gosh!" "Oh, my goodness!"
"Oh, my goodness! So, everything is understandable!"
In terms of population, the West faces only tens of millions of people in one country.
So, they may struggle to imagine periodical problems
brought by a population of more than one billion.
It's an important reason for their misunderstanding that
they lack the practical experience.
Behind this is the so-called stereotypes.
I met a French couple when I travelled in Guilin.
They needed help to find the restroom.
I can speak a little french. So, I went to help.
They told me, Guilin is a beautiful place.
I replied, yes, indeed.
Then, they asked me: "But there's something unusual.
Why are there no [political] slogans anymore and no one holds them now?"
- No more slogans!
- They still think there would be slogans!
"It's strange that China is totally different from what we have known."
I replied: "Are you time travelling? 40 years have passed..."
- They are time travellers.
- How have you spent the past 40 years?
These kinds of stereotypes have to be discarded.
They know so little about us.
After the development of the past one hundred
years in the West,
they know little about other countries apart from their own,
not only about China, but also others,
like India, or about the African countries
It's interesting that because of the Western
misinterpretations, misunderstandings and prejudices,
we Chinese have reflected deeply on ourselves since 1840, for a long time.
We have done the reflection most actively!
They said the system was problematic.
Okay, we modified it.
Then, our culture was said to be naturally defective.
Finally, our race was defined as flawed.
We have to construct a theory on our advantages and our future development.
This will be responsible for the young generations
who care about our country so much.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
[Co-producer: Guan Video]
Hello, everyone. Welcome to China Now.
We come here to position China and to understand China.
Beside me is the main guest of our show, Professor Zhang Weiwei.
He is the Director of China Institute of Fudan University.
Professor Zhang will first give today's keynote speech.
Then, it will be Q&A time.
We look forward to discussions between you and Professor Zhang.
- Now, it's time for the Prof. Zhang.
- Thank you.
I am always wondering why the West cannot understand China.
In my opinion, one important reason is their ideological prejudice.
A second reason is the perspective of eurocentrism.
They cannot imagine and understand a country
formed from a culture lasting for thousands of years.
You may remember that in 2016,
German president Gauck gave a speech at Tongji University in Shanghai.
He used to be a dissident in the German Democratic Republic.
He suggested in his speech that China is somewhat like East Germany.
This idea is common for many Westerners
— I have known so many.
They view China as an “East Germany in a larger size”,
and expect a color revolution to take place in China.
And I always tell them that China is quite different from East Germany,
at least in the following aspects:
Firstly, China is a highly open country.
Trips going abroad amount to 100 million annually,
while East Germany closed its borders.
Also, China is the world’s largest country in terms of goods trade.
Secondly, many Westerners compare the relationship
between the mainland and Taiwan
to the relationship between East Germany and West Germany.
They think that Taiwan represents the future direction of development,
and that people in the mainland envy the life in Taiwan so much
that they may even flood into Taiwan like people in East
Germany flooding into West Germany.
So, I told him that the relationship between the mainland
and Taiwan is just the opposite.
If we have to politicize everything like some Westerners do,
today, it is the Taiwanese who vote with their feet.
I estimate that there are about 500,000 people
from Taiwan in the greater Shanghai area.
And no less than 2 million Taiwanese now work or study in the mainland.
The total population of Taiwan is only 23 million, which is smaller than Shanghai’s.
Speaking frankly, we don’t want to politicize everything,
as some of them are meaningless.
But Westerners like to do so.
So, we might have no other choice than to join their discussion.
I have made many predictions about Taiwan’s future.
One of them is that Taiwanese are going from "hope to disappointment"
after they democratized under the Western political model
and they will fall into desperation without the mainland’s help.
In my eyes, this is the general trend of development
in Taiwan over the past two decades.
Thirdly, the West tends to misunderstand Chinese national characteristics.
That’s what I want to discuss with you:
China is not “another East Germany in a larger size”,
not a common country,
but a “civilizational state”.
So, China’s rise is not the rise of a common country,
but the rise of a “civilizational state”.
I formally proposed this idea eight years ago, in 2011,
in my book "China Wave - The Rise of A Civilizational State".
It has been translated into around 10 languages,
and overall has been well received at home and abroad.
This, I think, at least shows that many people agree with
or are interested in the concept of “civilizational state”.
So, today, I‘d like to discuss some analysis I have on this idea with you.
What is the “civilizational state”?
It refers to a country like ours which has an ancient
culture that has continued for thousands of years
and almost entirely overlaps with an enormous modern country.
This is her uniqueness.
I may even say that this feature is somehow like a gene.
It fundamentally decided the blueprint of China’s [political] system, its way of development and its behavioral pattern.
We all know the “four ancient civilizations”.
But, except China, the history of the other three civilizations was interrupted due to many reasons.
The Egyptians today have no relations with Pharaohs or Pyramids at all.
They don’t share the same nation, the blood, and the scripts with the ancient Egyptians.
They migrated [to the Nile] after the ancient Egyptian civilization disappeared.
While we Chinese are the original residents in our land,
and our culture lasts through thousands of years.
To help you understand “civilizational state”,
I should first introduce the concept of “nation state” to you.
The “nation state" in modern Western political
discourse is almost equal to “modern state”.
The “nation state” entails the well-known concepts of
like national sovereignty, territorial integrity,
sovereign equality,
national identity,
obligation to the military service,
clearly divided borders,
national anthem, national flag, and national emblem
which we are the symbols of a nation.
But the consciousness of nationality and “nation state”
needs to be constructed rather than being born with.
Singapore became independent in 1965.
In Mr. Lee Kuan Yew's memoir, the majority of the
Singaporean population were Chinese and Malays,
and also a small group of Indians.
Most of the Chinese still thought they were citizens of China,
and Malay thought they were members of Malaysia.
So, Mr. Li intentionally pushed forward the construction of the Singaporean nationality.
This is a classic example.
In history, most of European countries are religious
countries, or family countries, like the Habsburgs.
They fought with each other endlessly, and the blood of
the dead streamed through history.
Finally, the 30 Years' War in the early 17th century
caused almost a quarter of the Germanic population to disappear.
Then in 1648,
the famous Westphalian Treaty was signed.
To some extent, this treaty somehow
started the construction of "nation-states",
but its rapid development actually happened
during the 18th to 19th centuries.
So, nationalism rose in Europe as a political movement,
and “nation states” emerged as a result.
France is the first European country to form as a “nation state”.
Using its imperial power, it unified taxation and the army,
which pushed forward the French consciousness
for the nation-state to form.
With this consciousness, France greatly increased its
ability in war mobilization,
and easily defeated Prussia,
which consisted of about 300 loosely-connected Germanic states
before the German unification.
Then, Bismarck, the German Chancellor
known for his speech "Blood and Iron",
by "befriending distant enemies and attacking the near ones",
pushed forward the unification of Germany and the establishment of the German “nation state”.
Germany then developed rapidly.
In Asia, Japan also transformed itself into a “nation
state” through the Meiji Restoration,
and joined with the European powers.
It defeated China, which was a traditional and sluggish country,
in the First Sino-Japanese War [1894-1895].
The journey we Chinese have taken to build a
modern nation state is tough and arduous.
Traditionally, most of the Chinese population lived in rural areas.
They live in self-sufficient, closed and patriarchal-feudal societies
in which people in one village are from one family, and share one family name.
The men who were more educated than other villagers
played the role of judge and mediator of conflicts in the village.
Although in the ancient political system,
an emperor appeared to have infinite power,
in fact, his is "skies away from the grassroots".
The central government lacked efficient means for modern state management.
The Emperor’s rein mostly relied on the preaching of morality.
Starting from 1840, the Opium War,
China was defeated,
but the Chinese hadn’t realized the indicated crisis.
The Great Qing lost to powerful Western
countries
but the ceded lands were considered relatively marginal to China.
What really shocked the Chinese was the First Sino-Japanese War in 1894.
China, as a great power, was defeated by Japan, whom
China had never treated seriously.
After the signing of the Treaty of Shimonoseki,
for the first time, in May 1985, a Chinese official,
Yan Fu wrote about “saving the dying nation”,
and then through the central and local governments,
people urged to “save our country”, and “save our nation [bloodline]”.
Yan Fu also translated "Evolution and Ethics" into Chinese
and proposed the well-known
“Heaven's selection is the survival of the fittest”,
which explains the cruelty of competition between countries.
In 1902, Liang Qichao proposed the concept of the “Chinese Nation” for the first time:
the Chinese nation evolved from all ethnic groups within China's borders through thousands of years.
It is a fusion of all ethnicities,
and a unified family of diversity.
He also criticized Sun Yat-sen’s slogan
“Expel the Manchus and restore China “
because he thought this implied Han was superior to other ethnicities.
Later, Sun Yet-sen accepted this criticism and the
concept of a whole “Chinese nation”.
Liang Qichao repeatedly said
that traditional Chinese people were only aware of the imperial court and had no idea of the nation.
The central government had no modern armies,
no modern public finance,
so the commoners had no concept of “nation”.
If you refer to the Japanese description of China at that time,
they viewed China as a collection of autonomous tribes
that were divided and warring against with each other.
These people wore a hollow cap called “China” the country,
but under this cap was "a sheet of loose sand".
The concept of China as a country
had appeared very early in history,
but it was not a modern state,
rather, a series of dynasties,
a general reference to the combination of
states and ruling families.
At that time, people said that the country was “a country under one family, rather than a country of all families”.
Fei Xiaotong also said that,
as a national entity that exists,
the Chinese nation was formed during the course of thousands of years of history,
but as a national entity conscious of itself,
it was not until the last century
when China came into confrontations with the Western powers.
The national entity has always existed.
But the awareness of "I am Chinese"
didn't form until our one hundred years of modern history.
Only in modern times,
when the Chinese nation really clashed with the nations that are alien from ours,
did the Chinese begin to realize we have a national identity
and to develop national consciousness.
The Chinese felt that the “Chinese nation” is a community
in which people share the same space, the same culture, the same way of life, and are inter-dependent.
When the First Sino-Japanese War of 1894 started,
commoners felt it’s a “war of the court”,
even “the war of General Li Hongzhang”.
But this attitude was changed during the Second Sino-Japanese War [1937-1945].
The brutal invasion of Japanese militarists
brought not only [physical] disasters but also
a blow on the mentality of Chinese commoners.
It was a catalyst for awakening the “Chinese nation”.
Therefore, as we sing in the national anthem
“March of the Volunteers”,
“As Chinese nation faces its greatest peril,
"From each one the urgent call to action comes forth.”
That was when the “China nation” finally came into being.
Zhu Ziqing described his feeling he had.
“Finally, the so-called ‘sick man of East Asia' begins to revive."
"The ‘sleeping lion’ is awakened as expected."
"The dead China, the sheet of loose sand in the past,
is now a lively land in its flesh!“
After 14 years of the Second Sino-Japanese War,
Chinese people finally drove the invaders out of our land,
sweeping away the humiliation that had lasted for 100 years.
In this sense, we can better understand Chairman Mao’s
announcement to the world
on October 1st, 1949, that the Chinese people have since then stood up,
We can understand Marshal Peng Dehuai’ s famous comment after China’s victory of the Korean War
that the history when imperialist countries could conquer an Eastern country or nation with canons will never repeat itself.
In other words, an awakened, highly-unified modern nation state was born.
Last time, I talked about why in the First Opium War in 1840,
China was defeated,
although the total GDP of China was larger than that of Britain.
It’s because Britain was already a modern “nation state”.
It had very strong ability in war mobilization and other abilities of modern countries.
Meanwhile, China was a traditional country like a sheet of loose sand.
The people had very weak national consciousness.
But in the Korean War, after the founding of the People’s Republic of China,
Chinese armies could systematically destroy the British army.
This difference comes from the great changes in the historical background.
In terms of the construction of a modern country,
I’d like to share with you the opinion of a historian, Huang Renyu.
Taking a historical overview of modern Chinese history,
he divides the construction of modern China into several periods.
He sees the period from Sun Yat-sen's Republic of China [ROC] to 1949, the founding of the People's Republic of China [PRC]
as a phase in China's national construction.
According to him, the ROC period built the initial “upper structures” of a modern country,
including all the institutions in a modern government,
but this organization could not communicate with the
“lower structures” of China.
He said China under the Kuomintang had a top-heavy political structure.
He believed that the land revolution led by the
Chinese Communist Party [CCP]
reshaped the “lower structures”
by organizing peasant movements,
mobilizing armies to the frontline,
and through land reform and literacy education.
Even today, in relatively backward areas in China,
for example, in the “helping the poor” projects
in the mountains of Guizhou Province,
we have "digital management" — the government can directly remit money to bank accounts of the poor families
They have a bank card with an account number
and their account is linked with their mobile phones.
This is not easy.
I have been to many African countries. Governments
there cannot do this even today.
They are unable to make the policy reach grassroots communities.
AIDS is a serious problem in African countries,
while the governments feel it’s hard to give away AIDS
medicine to the people.
I am just commenting on the construction of the “lower structures” of a modern country.
Huang Renyu also proposes that the Reform-and-Open beginning in 1978
reshaped the “middle structure” of China,
that is to say,
the judiciary, governmental supervision, taxation,
logistics and other systems
which match with and support a modern market
economy, modern society, and modern country.
Through efforts of a hundred years,
we have built a strong modern country
with three layers: top, middle, bottom.
We have formed a modern country that has a unified government,
a unified market,
unified economy, education, national defense,
unified diplomacy, finance,
currency and taxation and so on.
All are necessary to a modern country.
But our country is different, or quite different from other countries.
Many of our old traditions haven’t disappeared with the
founding of a modern state.
On the contrary, they remain,
and even further develop themselves in the modern country.
That’s what I want to talk about the “civilizational state”.
Three scholars can be related to this concept.
The first one is American scholar in political culture, Lucian Pye.
He believes that China is not very likely to be built as a modern state
with the modern judiciary, national defense, or modern economy.
Many of the public intellectuals in China hold the same opinion.
He calls China a “civilization-state”.
He explains that the "civilization" and the "state" are the same.
He has a famous comment: "China is a
civilization pretending to be a state".
He means that China is actually an ancient civilization,
not a modern state,
even though it seems to a country.
This is a pejorative comment.
The second scholar is Martin Jacques, my friend,
and a senior researcher at our China Institute.
He published a controversial book in 2009,
"When China Rules the World."
This name is alien to our Chinese thinking.
But the publisher insisted to use this name
— an attractive title would bring a better sale.
Different from Lucian Pye,
he elaborates rather neutrally and more positively on the concept “civilization-state”,
and he reaches a clear conclusion:
China will not develop like Western countries,
and China’s rise will change the world.
Now, this conclusion seems reasonable.
But Martin Jacques also claims that
there can be certain kinds of conflicts between China’s two features:
being a nation state and a traditional civilization.
For example, he thinks that China may, in some ways,
revive the “tribute system” which existed in the history of East Asia.
He also claims that Chinese, in fact, feel superior about their ethnicity,
which may challenge the current international order.
The third scholar is me.
Firstly, I think China is a modern country.
This is a conclusion I cautiously make
after I have studied China's mode and China's path.
But traits of the Chinese civilization also make China a
modern country different from others.
Indeed, it has combined the advantages of the ancient
culture with those of the modern culture.
And I have mentioned this last time:
wherever we live,
the Chinese nation is the most hard-working and the most active in the world.
We're determined to change our fate.
This is also the mildest nation.
All these features lead to China’s rise today.
China has accepted some basic concepts of modern countries,
such as equality of sovereignty, human rights,
so China will not restore the tribute system,
or accept racial superiority.
That’s why I call it a “civilizational state”.
It is different from the “civilization-state”.
"Civilization-state" contains two concepts with equal weights,
whereas in "civilizational state",
"civilizational" describes the “modern state”.
So, the concept “civilizational state” is more positive
than Lucian Pye’s concept the “civilization-state”.
My basic idea is that a “civilizational state” inherits
abundant historical and cultural legacies,
so it will not follow every step of other countries.
It is able to absorb the advantages of other civilizations
without losing its own identity.
It can make a large number of creative contributions to the global culture.
I have said this a lot:
In order to expand the influence of the Chinese language, we need not cater for preferences of English.
Just as Sun-Tzu's The Art of War doesn’t need approval from Clausewitz,
or Confucius the approval of Plato,
or China’s macro-economic regulation the approval of the Fed.
It's more likely ... or have already happened
that the Chinese language may gradually influence English or other languages.
Sun-Tzu’s The Art of War has already changed, and will
continue to change, Western military doctrine.
Confucius and Plato have all provided precious wisdom to this world.
As for China’s macro-economic regulation,
I do believe America can learn a lot from it
(laughs)
but to do so can be hard.
Then, we will come back to the question at the beginning of my speech.
Why does the West always misunderstand China?
Because the West always interprets China based on
their limited experience from their history
and the discourses formed from these experiences,
such as “west centrism”,
“eurocentrism”, or “the end of the history”.
These are the lenses through which they view China.
Their logic [of development] begins from totalitarianism,
to authoritarianism,
then finally, ends at the Western democracy.
Under this logic, the development of history is linear,
and it terminates at the Western political system.
This is absurd in our eyes.
The rise of a civilizational country follows a totally different logic.
In history, China was ahead of the West for a long time
for an important reason — I will call it "reason one".
Then, in the 18th century, China was left behind by the West,
which taught us a profound lesson.
After decades of efforts, we have finally caught up with the West,
and even surpassed it in some areas.
I call the reasons for this success "reason two".
Historically speaking, reason two inherits and furthur develops reason one.
Why China was ahead of the West in history and why we could catch up or even surpass
is linked by historical inheritance and development.
For instance, in history, we have a people-centered tradition.
"People are the foundation of a country; peace is guaranteed when this foundation is solid.” [Book of Documents by Confucius]
The priority of the government is people, and improving
people’s living materially and spiritually.
However, the biggest problem of the Western model today,
no matter in Western or non-Western countries,
is the “idle spinning" of the political machine.
The government can't effectively improve people’s living.
As a result, the Western system is facing a decline in
both the Western and non-Western world.
Behind this are two philosophical outlooks.
One is about West-centrism, a linear outlook of philosophy.
In this view, people believe they have the best system,
and others should work hard to reach the same system.
On the contrary, in the Chinese conception of history,
all kinds of systems have coexisted,
and sometimes even been in conflict with each other.
A system might have worked well,
however, we say "prideful people will forget to make further progress",
and they can be easily surpassed by others.
The competition in Chinese
history is multiple-tracked and dynamic.
Next week I’m going to talk about
the "four supers” of our civilizational state:
super large population scale, super vast territory,
super long history and super rich cultural accumulation.
This is the most amazing part in the rise of China and will astonish the world.
That’s all for today’s speech. Thank you!
The applause is for Professor Zhang.
Thank you for your speech. Please take a seat.
I majored in language studies
and I'm impressed with one thing in Professor’s speech
— the power inherited with the language we passed on.
There was a scholarly trend to abandon Chinese characters during the Republic of China.
It was found impracticable after a series of exploration, trials and failures.
Just like you said, it would conflict with our national basis.
Why? Obviously, it is due to a large number of homophones.
To carry on the traditions of a civilizational state,
things must be done according to native customs and features.
I totally agree with that.
In some cases, we might lose our own features in internationalization.
So never forget your own identities.
I deeply resonated with one point in Professor Zhang's speech.
When we were elementary students, we read from the textbook that
the Chinese people were hardworking and diligent.
We felt it was hollow because all nations are hardworking.
But it's not so.
Now we realize Chinese people are truly hardworking.
It isn't joking.
Some of my colleagues traveled to Europe.
They found people get off work early in the afternoon at about four o'clock.
They would order a cup of coffee, sit on the beach.
A whole afternoon would pass.
They would spend the afternoon like this, drinking coffee to the sea.
Not until that time did they realize the appraisal of our diligence was pertinent.
It's the truth.
Probably we have been too used to our diligence
just as we have taken our ancient civilization for granted.
We even forgot to study it.
Now it's time for Q&As.
Put up your hands if you have any questions.
Please pass the microphone to him.
Professor Zhang, I’ve seen many of your shows.
We say "seek truth from facts".
Any theory or viewpoint has to go through a developing period.
In the case of Taiwan,
I’m wondering whether we can redefine the
policy “one country, two systems”.
Personally, I’m doubting if they are using
“the 1992 Consensus” as an ATM password.
Once they get the preferential policies from the mainland,
they are likely to purchase weapons [with the money].
To be honest, if a war broke out across the Strait,
half of the bullets fired at the PLA would be those provided by ourselves.
Some people advise helping the KMT.
But have they ever considered how the KMT treated the Communist Party in the "April 12 Massacre"?
So, I’m wondering if we can re-evaluate the concept of “one country, two systems”
and keep it up with the times.
Would you mind telling us what area you work or research in?
I work in telecommunication.
But I am a military fan and fond of military reports.
I often say
one feature of China’s system is that we have a long-term strategy.
We don't "haggle over every ounce" with Taiwan
over the benefits given to it.
Taiwan’s independence has essentially become impossible.
Their economic connection and reliance on the mainland mean that
seeking independence is suicide.
There’s no need to send PLA,
because they would have collapsing stock and housing markets.
This is the most important reason
why China can keep a strategic focus.
Military fan as you are,
you may consider more about the techniques
like how the bullets shoot to the PLA.
But the war wouldn’t go in that way.
I want to add one more thing that
“The 1992 Consensus” is based on “One China”.
Some details may be expressed differently [by both sides].
And “one country, two systems” was a concept, a plan,
but now we are discussing “the Taiwan solution for one country, two systems”.
Although according to their internal reports,
not so many people support this,
there are still people who support this.
I also hope to rectify your view that
"We need to help the KMT".
I guess you haven't fully understood documents from President Xi.
We have faith in the representatives of Taiwan people and social groups
rather than the KMT, the DPP or any other parties.
But anyone supporting reunification and seeking peaceful development across the trait
are the people we are going to win support from.
So we’re giving benefits to our compatriots.
As Prof. Zhang said, we need to stay calm.
OK, let's see if anyone else has a question.
Go ahead, please.
I have a specific question.
A while ago, the "Constitution Amendment" made changes to the term limit of the country's top leader.
The amendment stimulated extensive discussion among my friends and some of their views are very sharp.
Our opinions may be partial,
I hope to hear a more comprehensive understanding from you, from a different perspective.
The Constitution of the CCP clearly stipulates the abolition of lifelong terms.
As long as the President is a member of the Communist Party of China,
he cannot be in office for the length of his life.
Last April, I gave a lecture on China’s rise and the China Mode at Yale University
a scholar raised the same question.
I answered former President Roosevelt served for four terms in the United States,
as well as former Chancellor Adenauer and current Chancellor Merkel in Germany.
Roosevelt and Adenauer are recognized as outstanding leaders in these two countries.
But you didn’t regard that as lifelong-term.
Those leaders served four terms without the constitution declaring the abolition of a lifelong system.
But you’re not suspicious of them.
That’s a contradiction.
I believe the design of a political system must include strategies for best and worst situations.
The worst situations may be the leader’s retirement for health reasons or limited ability.
We still preserve the system of collective leadership — democratic centralism.
Meanwhile, in the best situation,
our system needs to allow outstanding talents to achieve high.
Thank you, Prof. Zhang.
With respect to this question, I have a follow-up.
We've passed the 40the anniversary of reform and opening up, and we have entered the 41st year.
On the road to reform, what can we change and what should we hold up to?
Is there a clear boundary?
Since you asked about the constitutional amendment,
The key point lies in the first Article in the constitution
which defines the leadership of the CCP as the essence of socialism with Chinese characteristics.
I’ve also studied that
the CCP and the Western political parties are both named as parties,
but they are not the same.
The English word “party” and “parti” in French
share the same language origin “part”,
which means a section.
Therefore, the concept of Western political parties can be explained very simply,
that is, society is composed of different interest groups.
Each group represents the interests of some people and these groups compete.
You win even if it's 51% against 49%.
Such is their logic.
But things are different in China.
Why is China regarded as a civilizational state?
Its most important feature is that it is integrated from hundreds of small states over time.
If such a country adopts the party system with partial interests like Western countries,
it would soon disintegrate.
Maybe there would be a Shanghai Party, Beijing Party,
Tianjin Party, Wuxi Party, Jinan Party,
and then wars would break out.
Therefore, frankly speaking, ever since Qin Shi Huang unified China,
we've only had a unified ruling group most of the time.
And the ruling groups were mainly Confucian groups.
As I often tell Americans,
China has mostly been under the leadership of a single party
but we were far ahead of the West most of the time.
And the magnitude of adjustment in internal policies is far greater than in America,
where the adjustments of policies are between Republicans and Democrats.
By contrast, our policy adjustments from the Cultural Revolution to Reform and Opening-up were all made within the CCP.
These changes are far greater than the changes between the Republican Party and the Democratic Party.
But we were able to achieve that.
I would say, the Western parties are partial-interest groups while China has a representtive of its collective interest.
That’s the biggest difference.
And you can view the West from this perspective.
You can ask foreigners, is there any party in your country representing the collective interest?
- Few.
- This is our unique skill.
We've gone all the way to this day.
Institutional acceptance must be established.
This is our confidence about our system.
We love our country,
and we accept the entire institutional arrangement based on the Constitution of the PRC.
It may not be perfect.
That’s why we have been seeking reform and improvement.
But the foundation is not to be shaken.
As I often say, the biggest change during President Xi’s presidency
comes from his sincere hope that the intellectuals can form institutional acceptance.
In the past 40 years, China has developed from a poor country to the second largest economy,
the biggest trading state with the most foreign exchange reserve.
700 to 800 million people have been pulled out of poverty,
which is an achievement never seen in human history.
We must be clear about what we have done.
I agree with Qin Zhuo. Thank you.
Thanks for showing your approval.
Anyone else has a question?
Nice to see you, Professor Zhang.
Many people say “The Chinese civilization no longer exists since the collapse of the Ming Dynasty”.
It means traditional Chinese civilization is no longer intact after the Ming Dynasty.
Prof. Zhang, when you talk about “civilizational state”,
does it mean we’re going to restore the "orthodox" Chinese civilization?
Different views can be discussed and debated.
We are not at all afraid of competition.
China, be confident.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
China, as a long and far-reaching civilization,
has experienced so many ups and downs in history.
but the fact is its civilization has not been interrupted.
As long as Chinese characters are still in use,
the civilization will not disappear.
As long as you understand two or three hundred chengyu idioms,
the basics of Chinese morals are in your blood.
These couldn't be interrupted. It’s the key point.
So don’t come to a conclusion easily that our civilization was cut.
This is my first piece of advice.
Secondly, we must keep pace with time.
The inclusiveness of Chinese culture is unique all around the world,
which can be seen from the supplementation among Confucianism, Buddhism and Taoism.
When I was in Taiwan, they asked me,
"Do you still have the Chinese culture? It was totally repudiated since the Cultural Revolution."
However, after my travels to over a hundred countries,
I found that Chinese culture existed everywhere.
There's no way to repudiate it.
The culture always remains in Chinese people's daily life.
So need a broader outlook when we talk about how Chinese culture can be inherited and influence the world.
I think the most significant feature of Chinese culture is constant integration.
Even to this day, it is still evolving and absorbing good things from other cultures.
Still “incorporating things of a diverse nature”.
Anyone else has any questions?
Hello Professor Zhang, what positive experience do you think
our current "socialist system with Chinese characteristics" absorbs from our ancient political system?
Could I chip in a word? I what field do you work or study?
I'm an interior designer.
Oh really?
Then why would you be interested in this question?
I have been interested in our traditional culture since high school.
I know we’ve been so aggrieved since the Opium War.
Fortunately, we are growing stronger with the efforts of dedicated patriots over the last century,
especially after the founding of CCP and the 40 years’ reform and opening up.
Now we are talking about cultural confidence.
As a part of the traditional culture,
what merits of the ancient political system have been inherited and reserved?
You seem to be a devoted fan of Chinese history and culture.
Have a seat.
Although he works as an interior designer,
he's also devoting himself to design our society.
That's awesome.
Different views can be discussed and debated.
We are not at all afraid of competition.
China, be confident.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
That’s a great question.
Almost all our success today has its own historical heritage.
For instance, the improvement of people’s living standard is our biggest success.
It comes from our traditional people-centered doctrine,
in which “people are the foundation of a nation and it will be stable only if the foundation is solid.”
Another example is our meritocratic system for selecting and appointing officials.
It is actually a continuation and development of the imperial examination system, but with new components.
Lip service is not acceptable in this selection system.
You must be qualified.
You must have work experience and good performance.
Almost all the developed areas in China are equipped with a combination of three factors:
historical heritage,
modern factors and sometimes elements of the
“red culture” [communist revolutions].
Professor Zhang has given a keynote speech on the topic of "civilizational state"
and it inspired so many questions.
I enjoy such dialogue so much.
But I'm afraid there's not enough time for more questions.
You can keep your questions for the next episode.
Professor Zhang has previewed that he will give a deep illustration of the features of "civilizational state".
We look forward to that. Let's thank Professor Zhang.
And thanks everyone for joining us.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组